A Guide to the Rives Family Papers, 1841-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Rives Family Papers, 1841-1865
The Library of Virginia
24065
.1 cubic feet
Rives Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 10 November 1953, from Elizabeth R. Snead, Scottsville, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Robert Rives (1798-1869) was born in Nelson County, Virginia, and attended the College of William and Mary, graduating in 1817. He represented Nelson County, Virginia, in the House of Delegates from 1823 to 1829. After his service in the House of Delegates, he moved to Albemarle County. Rives was one of the wealthiest men in Virginia before the Civil War began, but lost most of his fortune during the Civil War. He married Elizabeth Pannill (1811-1895), daughter of Samuel Pannhill of Campbell County, Virginia, in 1841, and they had one child, Cornelia E. Rives (1845-1910), who married Charles Carter Harrison (1842-1882) in 1866. Harrison served as a lieutenant in Company I, 46th Virginia Infantry, and after the Civil War was a prosperous farmer in Albemarle County.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1841-1865, of the Rives family of Albemarle County, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1848-1863, from Alfred T. Harris and Harris and Gibson of Richmond, Virginia, to Robert Rives concerning Rives' agricultural and stock interests, the sale of slaves, Rives' accounts, and a Union assault on Drewry's Bluff in 1862; letters, 1855-1862, from Samuel Nowlin of Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives discussing property Nowlin manages for Rives in Lynchburg; and letters, 1861-1864, from Charles C. Harrison of the 46th Virginia Infantry to Cornelia E. Rives concerning camp life, the Peninsular campaign, the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks), and his love for Cornelia. Papers also include letters, 1841-1864, to and from members of the Rives family concerning personal news, agricultural information, the stationing of cavalry Charlottesville, Virginia, and the wounding of Charles Harrison and letters, 1864, from Harrison to his sister Rosalie Harrison concerning camp life; and miscellaneous accounts and papers, 1865 and no date, of Cornelia E. Rives.
Contents List
- Letters and Accounts, Alfred T. Harris and Harris and Gibson to Robert Rives, 1848-1863. (Folder 1)
  - Account and letter, 23 May 1848, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, Virginia, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, Virginia, concerning the sale of Rives' tobacco and his bonds in the James River and Kanawha Company.
  - Letter, 15 July 1848, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' wheat and tobacco, whiskey for Rives, and dividends from the James River and Kanawha Company bonds.
  - Account and letter, 5 August 1848, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' tobacco and wheat, noting the poor market for the latter.
  - Letter, 23 January 1849, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and noting that he has sent the blacksmith tools Rives ordered.
  - Letter, 21 July 1849, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and the market for wheat.
  - Letter, 11 August 1849, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating he has purchased state stock for Rives and commenting on the price of wheat.
  - Letter, 20 October 1849, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning a purchase of state stock for Rives and the sale of Rives' wheat.
  - Letter, 23 July 1850, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, sending items Rives purchased, as well as the stock Rives purchased in the James River and Kanawha Company, and commenting on the wheat market.
  - Letter, 3 August 1850, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock bought for Rives, bacon shipped to Rives, and the sale of Rives' wheat crop.
  - Letter, 8 August 1851, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that he has bought state stock for Rives, and commenting on the wheat market.
  - Letter, 1 December 1851, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concering a purchase of state stock for Rives and the sale of one of Rives' slaves.
  - Account and letter, 4 August 1852, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the sale of Rives' wheat, the purchase of state stock, and the shipping of two french bedsteads to Rives.
  - Letter, 17 January 1853, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' interest and dividends, state stock, and a shipment of sugar to Rives.
  - Letter, 1 July 1853, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning state stock and the wheat market.
  - Account, 30 June 1853, of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson.
  - Account, 31 December 1853, of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson.
  - Letter, 3 July 1854, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' tobacco and a city certificate of debt.
  - Letter, 21 July 1854, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating they have received his certificate of deposit on the Bank of Virginia, and noting that there is cholera in Richmond.
  - Letter, 31 May 1855, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, regarding the purchase of state stock.
  - Account, 31 December 1856, of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson, along with letter, 2 January 1857, concerning his account.
  - Letter, 28 October 1857, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of state stock, money from the sale of Rives' wheat, and the current slave market.
  - Letter, 6 November 1857, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' purchase of state stock and the wheat market.
  - Account, 21 May 1858, of Robert Rives with Harris and Gibson for sale of tobacco.
  - Letter, 4 February 1859, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, regarding the purchase of state stock for Rives.
  - Letter, 8 July 1859, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that Rives' interest and dividends will be collected and state stock purchased.
  - Letter, 12 July 1859, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning his dividends on bank stock and interest from state stock, as well as purchase of state stock.
  - Letter, 3 August 1859, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' check on the Bank of Scottsville for the purchase of state stock.
  - Account and letter, 21 September 1859, from Harris and Gibson, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of 57 bags of guano.
  - Letter, 6 February 1860, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning Rives' bonds in the James River and Kanawha Company, his dividends and interest, and the tobacco market.
  - Letter, 9 March 1860, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the inspection and sale of Rives' tobacco in Richmond.
  - Letter, 25 July 1860, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, regarding the purchase of state stock for Rives, and the James River and Kanawha Company's unwillingness to pay interest on its bonds.
  - Letter, 30 July 1860, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the purchase of state stock and asking if Rives wants to convert his Jaems River and Kanawha bonds into state stock.
  - Letter, 7 December 1860, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, concerning the conversion of Rives' James River and Kanawha bonds into state stock, banks discounting, the dull stock market, and the downward turn of the tobacco and wheat markets.
  - Letter, 9 January 1861, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, stating that he has collected Rives' dividends from the Bank of Virginia and the Farmers' Bank as well as his interest from state stock, and commenting on the possibility of civil war.
  - Letter, 16 May 1862, from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, asking Rives to hold on to an envelope for him, commenting on Richmond during wartime, an attack by Union gunboats on Drewery's Bluff, the departure of civilians and wounded soldiers from Richmond, and news of Harris' son who took part in a fight at Giles Court House. He also comments on the stock market.
  - Letter, 15 July 1863 from Alfred T. Harris, Richmond, to Robert Rives, Richmond, stating that he has collected Rives' dividends and interest and placed them in the Bank of Virginia, sending a certificate. Harris also sends news that the enemy had been repulsed at Jackson, Mississippi.
- Letters, Samuel Nowlin to Robert Rives, 1855-1862. (Folder 2)
  - Letter, 7 November 1855, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that C. Jordan, Rives' tenant on property in Lynchburg is moving out and promises to pay money owed. Nowlin adds that he will fix up the property and rent it again.
  - Letter, 31 December 1855, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating he has distrained Jordan for the rent and adding what repairs he will make to the house.
  - Letter, 8 February 1856, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he has received the rent he distrained from Jordan and commenting on the needed repairs.
  - Letter, 31 March 1856 from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, informing Rives of the death of his [Nowlin's] son. Nowlin comments on a new door for the house and asking Rives to come look at the house.
  - Letter, 24 February 1857, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, concerning his efforts to find a renter for Rives' property and mentioning that someone was interested in purchasing it. Nowlin adds that the house needs some repairs.
  - Letter, 9 May 1857, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he had received some back rent owed, but that it won't cover repairs, that a new tenant has moved in, and that a stone wall surrounding the lot has collapsed. He comments about repairs to the wall.
  - Letter, July 1857, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, concerning repairs to the stone wall on Rives' property.
  - Letter, 16 February 1858, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, stating that he has not found a new renter for the property.
  - Letter, 28 March 1862, from Samuel Nowlin, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Robert Rives, sending a certificate of deposit, stating that the renter would like a reduced rent for the following year, and commenting on the condition of the house and yard.
- Letters, Charles C. Harrison to Cornelia Rives, 1861-1865. (Folder 3)
  - Letter, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, concerning life in camp, the lack of religion, and his love for Cornelia.
  - Letter, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, commenting on the marching he has done, stating that he was elected first lieutenant of his company, and adding his thoughts of Cornelia sustain him.
  - Letter, 31 May 1862, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, describing the beginning of the battle of Seven Pines (Fair Oaks), camp conditions, and professing his love for Cornelia.
  - Letter, 19 November 1862, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Richmond, concerning his love for Cornelia.
  - Letter, 5 October 1864, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to Cornelia E. Rives, Albemarle County, concerning his love for Cornelia.
- Letters of the Rives Family, 1841-1865. (Folder 4)
  - Letter, 7 April 1841, from Robert Rives, Albemarle County, to Elizabeth Pannill, Campbell County, Virginia, sending personal news and professing his love for her.
  - Letter, 19 June 1852, from Samuel Pannill, Campbell County, to Robert Rives, Albemarle County, sending personal and local news, and commenting on the tobacco and wheat crops.
  - Letter, 12 December 1859, from Elizabeth Pannill Rives, Albemarle County, to Cornelia E. Rives sending local, family, and personal news, and adding that she misses her.
  - Letter, 24 April 1861, from Elizabeth Rives, Albemarle County, to Cornelia E. Rives sending local and family news, commenting on the preparations for war, and commenting on the people in Maryland.
  - Letter, 19[?] October 1863, from C. Edward Rives, at the University of Virginia, to his cousin, possibly Cornelia E. Rives, sending social and personal news.
  - Letter, 13 February 1864, from C. Edward Rives, University of Virginia, to his sister Eleanor Rosalie Rives sending personal and social news, and adding that the cavalry has been stationed in Charlottesville, Virginia.
  - Letter, 24 May 1864, from Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to his sister Rosalie Harrison providing general comments on the war and camp life, and stating he misses Cornelia Rives.
  - Letter, 1 June 1864, Charles C. Harrison, 46th Virginia Infantry, to his sister Rosalie Harrison containing news on camp life and the regiment.
  - Letter, no date, from an unknown writer to Cornelia E. Rives stating that Charles C. Harrison had been slightly wounded and that Harrison was thinking of her.
- Accounts and Miscellaneous Items of Cornelia E. Rives, 1865 and no date. (Folder 5)
  - Account, 1 December[?] 1865, of Cornelia E. Rives with William N. Bell and Company, Richmond, for clothing items.
  - Account, 13 December 1865, of Cornelia E. Rives with William N. Bell and Company, Richmond, for clothing items.
  - Account, no date, of Miss Rives with A. A. Housewright for clothing items and headwear.
  - Account, no date, of Cornelia Rives with R. Ferrandin[?] for hair and makeup products.
  - Account, no date, of Miss Rives with E. V. A. Place[?] for clothing items.
  - Invitation, 24 June no year, to attend the celebration of the Brookland and Piedmont Literary Societies at Brookland School.